Natural weapons come in various forms,
functions, and styles, and today I'm
going to explain them all to you. Let's
start with a smile and talk teeth. You
may not think it, but this crocodile has
bitten off more than it can chew. But
that's only because crocodiles don't
chew. Instead, they violently twist and
spin their body, dismembering their prey
into easily swallowed chunks of flesh
and bone. aptly named the death roll
allows crocodiles and alligators to
disorient, kill, and consume large prey
animals, including at times humans.
Carnivorous mammals, on the other hand,
chew and grind the meat that they tear
off their prey. To make this more
efficient, they have multiple kinds of
teeth, like shearing incizers or
flattening mullers. But canines, the
sharp, exaggerated fangs found on
predators, are specifically evolved as
weapons used to clamp down on prey
animals and pierce through bone and
hide. Wolves and lions both use
complicated pack tactics in order to
isolate or ambush a member of a herd.
Wolves will play the long game, getting
in bites whenever they can and often
waiting for the prey to bleed out, while
lions prefer a more immediate approach.
One will grab the prey from behind while
another swings around, chomping down on
the neck, crushing the windpipe and
killing them instantly. Vampire bats use
their canines as more of a scalpel than
a stabbing tool. They smell where the
largest veins of their host are, then
cut small incisions there. They drool
over their food, letting the
anti-coagulants in their saliva prevent
the blood from clotting so that they can
lap up that freshly flowing blood. In
the past, there were several
saber-tooththed predators like the
smileon, a now extinct big cat that we
think used its massive sabers to slay
the megapana in the ice age. But when it
comes to teeth specialized for killing,
none have stood the test of time better
than sharks. Great white sharks have an
upper jaw filled with broad triangular
teeth. These are serrated like saws,
allowing them to shear off pieces of
flesh from anything unfortunate enough
to end up in their mouths. The teeth on
the lower jaw are more sharp and
pointed, which they use to make contact
first, holding the prey in place before
the upper jaw saw comes down and
completely shreds them apart. Because of
how aggressive sharks are as predators,
their teeth often fall out of their
gums. But this is accounted for because
behind their front row of teeth is a
conveyor belt of layers upon layers of
replacements ready to be put to use.
like snacks in a vending machine. When
one falls out, another is pushed forward
to take its place. Basking sharks can
have up to 200 teeth in their jaw at one
time. And it's estimated that some
species go through 30,000 teeth in their
lifetime. Even animals that are further
removed from us, like lamprays,
lobsters, and leeches, have developed
their own versions of teeth completely
independent from us. This is convergent
evolution, where basically the same
thing evolves twice. And this is going
to be a common theme in this video
because animals that face similar
pressures often develop similar
solutions. Both antlers and horns are
hard protrusions from the skull which
can be used as dangerous tools to swipe
or slam into adversaries. Horns are
found on bovids like bulls, big horn
sheep, bison, and impala. Their bony
cores sheathed in keratin, the same
thing that makes up our fingernails.
Rams use their horns to well ram.
smashing into opponents and easily
shattering bone. Battering rams are
siege weapons that we created and named
after the animal, often featuring their
heads carved in the front. So clearly,
ancient humans were traumatized enough
by rams to turn their strategy into a
weapon of their own. Texas long horns
have well long horns, which they sweep
from side to side in an area of effect
attack, making it difficult for
predators to approach their calves, even
from the sides. Today, due to selective
breeding, these horns regularly grow
more than 8 ft long. That's more than a
Victor Webbananyama on each side of the
skull. Antlers, on the other hand, are
found in servit like deers, moose, and
elk and are mainly used as a mating
device. The large display shows off how
impressive you are as a male and helps
to establish social dominance in a herd.
Watch these deer lock branches, twisting
and throwing each other in a gritty
wrestling match. Stags and moose
fighting like this can often be heard
echoing throughout the forest as big
antlers crash into each other and bigger
bodies crash into the ground. In some
species like elk and caribou, antlers
are sharp enough that fights commonly
end with puncturing the rival male in
the neck. While horns begin growing
shortly after birth and stay permanently
on the head, antlers are grown and shed
every mating season. They do share an
evolutionary origin, but it's clear they
took on different paths. Yet they still
remain used for similar scenarios. And
the same can be said for other head
weapons we find in nature. Giraffes have
bony protrusions called oicones which
they club into each other during necking
contests where the males fight for
mating rights and social dominance by
whipping their faces into each other.
Rhino horns are a bit different. They
have a uni horn comprised entirely of
keratin with no bony core. Rhinos may
jab, charge, or thrust with these horns,
defeating rivals or scaring away
predators that go after their calves.
But they also use them as a
multi-purpose tool for digging, clearing
paths, and as a pointer stick for
communication. Rhino beetles also have a
single horn on their head, which comes
in a variety of shapes such as upwards
and downwards curves or pitchforks. And
they mainly use these to fight off other
males. Poundfor-pound, rhino beetles are
one of the strongest animals in nature,
able to lift 850 times their own body
weight with the flick of the horn. And
the last unicorn I'll mention is the
narwhal, which sprouts a huge spiral
horn from their face. Though this is
actually a specialized tooth,
specifically the upper left canine,
which has evolved to be extremely long,
making it a tusk, not a horn. Tusks are
kind of like teeth for hornlike
purposes. They tend to be found on large
herbivores who don't have sharp teeth
otherwise. And they're used for mating
competitions, dominance displays, and
fending off predators, rarely for
eating. Musk deer don't grow antlers and
instead grow sharp tusks that are used
for malemale combat. And it's funny
because they look like little vampire
deers. But yeah, lots of animals like
elephants, walruses, and hippos, they
all use their tusks for essentially the
same stuff. So despite being literal
teeth, tusks are more similar to head
weapons like horns and antlers in their
use. But heads, sorry, I meant to say
head butts are also a viable method of
attack. The ultimate butt head being the
pachy sephilosaurus. These guys' skulls
were incredibly thick and exposed from
any ornamentation, and about 20% of them
we've found show previous damage on
their domes, implying that they did use
them non-randomly to smash into things.
It's typically thought that they smashed
heads in a first to get concussed
doesn't get the girl competition, but
this is actually unclear. It might
actually make more sense if they rammed
into each other's sides, but I think
that's less fun. Humans are also pretty
capable of using our skulls offensively.
Headbutts are actually one of our most
devastating moves, building up tons of
force in short distances. They're
completely banned in almost all combat
sports because of how fatal they can be.
But okay, let's flip this coin over and
go from heads to tails. Thresher sharks
have an extremely long scytheshaped
codle fin, which can sometimes be as
long as the body of the shark itself.
When hunting, they whip this tail,
swatting smaller fish and stunning them,
then easily gobbling them up. Monitor
lizards like Komodo dragons and Nile
monitors have muscular tails that they
swing side to side. These are strong
enough to knock adult humans off their
feet, cause internal injuries, or leave
you with a painful sting. But this is
obviously a secondary weapon to their
powerful bites. Similarly, orcas use
their tails primarily to swim. But they
are known to send things flying with an
upward smack of their tail. Sometimes
for the sake of a coordinated team hunt,
but other times just to be an [__]
Where we do see tails specifically as a
primary weapon is in animals of the
past. And Kyloaurus was covered in spiky
armor and had a large bony mass at the
end of their tail, which they swung
around as a powerful club-like weapon.
Stegosaurs had something similar in
their thagomizers, an arrangement of
spikeshaped plates on their tails, which
was most likely swung for defensive
purposes as well. Extinct relatives of
armadillos called gipadons were the size
of cars and they also had tail clubs.
But nowadays they aren't found on any
living animals. Does this mean that tail
clubs weren't that good of a weapon? No,
not necessarily. There are many things
to consider. The fact that animals often
have other options for natural weapons,
the other uses of a tail that you lose
if you attach a big ball of mass to the
end of it, and also dumb luck. Natural
selection works based on traits that
already exist, that are just good enough
to lead to more reproduction. The fact
that there are no tail clubs anymore
isn't a dig at tail clubs, rather a
complement to the other strategies that
exist and are working perfectly fine.
Also, Enkyosaurus was wiped out for
meteoric reasons. If that hadn't
happened, who's to say they wouldn't be
around still swinging that tail? But
regardless, there is a structure that we
find at the ends of tails today that may
be far more deadly than a simple club.
Stingers are sharp organs found at the
end of scorpion tails, as well as at the
bottoms of several insects. But we can't
really talk about them without first
discussing the real weapon here, which
is what stingers deliver. What do golden
dart frogs, Indian red scorpions, and
blue ringed octopus all have in common?
They all have colors in their name. Oh,
and they can each easily kill dozens of
humans despite being able to fit in the
palm of your hand. Toxicity is nature's
great equalizer. It allows what would
otherwise be a completely unthreatening,
helpless animal to be regarded as one of
the most dangerous in the world. Animals
like dart frogs are extremely poisonous
when ingested, so predators recognize to
avoid their bright colorations and don't
try to eat them. Others inject toxins
into their prey as an active weapon,
which we call venom instead of poison.
And I'm going to tell you about the most
venomous animals in the world. But
first, there's something of greater harm
to you that you should be aware of. If
you've been on the internet at all
lately, you've probably typed your
sensitive data into several websites.
And unfortunately, it's openly being
sold by data brokers and weaponized
against you through exploitative
targeted ads, increased scam messages,
and identity theft. It's unreal how much
information you can get just from
searching someone up. Phone numbers,
addresses, salaries, even the names of
family members. It seems impossible to
scrub your personal data from the
internet these days, which is why Incogn
is here to help. Incogn will
automatically handle the removal process
of your info from hundreds of known data
brokers. Even when your data inevitably
reappears on these sites, Incogns
to remove it again for you. On top of
this, with their custom removal feature,
you can send them any link and a
dedicated privacy expert will get your
info removed from that website. As a
creator and researcher, there is a lot
that I need to keep private, both for
personal and professional reasons. And
using Incogn, I'm able to feel at ease.
They're the only data removal service
that's been officially verified to
actually remove your information from
these data broker sites. So, I know that
it actively reduces how vulnerable I am
to scams, people trying to hack my
accounts, and even from stalkers.
Disappear from the internet and take
control of your privacy with incogn. Get
60% off any annual plan using code danin
blue or by clicking the link in the
description. Back to the video. Box
jellyfish are one of the most venomous
creatures in the world. Their tentacles
have specialized cells called
pneumaticists, which trigger when
something brushes against them,
launching microscopic harpoons at speeds
faster than a bullet, injecting a
cocktail of toxic proteins that'll kill
a human in only 5 minutes, the amount of
time it takes to die without a working
heart. The inland taipan is the only
other animal that can compare. commonly
cited to have the most potent venom of
any organism on the planet. If one bit
you, you actually wouldn't be in much
pain. First, you'd start to sweat, then
get dizzy and feel nauseous as the venom
silently seeps into your bloodstream.
Your eyelids begin to droop. You have
trouble speaking as your facial muscles
begin to fail you. Eventually, the
muscles you use to move fail you. Then,
the ones you use to breathe.
Additionally, your blood starts clotting
in random places, followed by
unstoppable bleeding when your body
inevitably runs out of blood clotting
factors. All in all, it'll take about 30
minutes for you to perish. Toxins are
distinct from each other in the
different ways they mess with your
natural systems. From Komodo dragons
that cause your blood not to clot and
keep bleeding out from where they bite
you to the digestive enzymes that melt
your insides as you get drunk by an
assassin bug. Some toxins make you feel
a pain that never goes away and some
make you so numb that you never feel
anything again. There are many delivery
methods of toxins as well. Snakes inject
venom through their fangs. Specialized
teeth connected to venom glands behind
their eyes. Arthropods like scorpions,
wasps, and bullet ants have stingers as
I mentioned before. And cone snails have
a long toothlike structure called a
radula which comes from their mouth to
inject venom and paralyze prey. Another
of the deadliest venoms in the world,
toxicity is the most powerful weapon in
nature, and it isn't even close. It
allows the tiniest of animals and even
unmoving plants to take down some of the
largest, most resilient fauna in nature.
And what's worse is that you don't
always know it's coming. While some
animals honestly display their toxicity
with colors and flashy structures, other
extremely venomous creatures can look
quite unassuming. Also, imagine the
times before information was so
accessible. You would never know if an
animal was safe to handle or if it could
kill you instantly until someone tried
it. There's this video of tourists
happily holding a blue ringed octopus,
which is genuinely one of the dumbest
things you could do ever. If it decided
to bite down at any time, the holder
would have fallen severely paralyzed and
perished in a few hours. So, toxins can
be injected in many ways, but they can
also be ejected as well. Spitting cobras
spray toxic fluid from their fangs,
mainly as a form of intimidation, as
their main weapon is still a venomous
bite. But this spray can still prove
fatal by seeping into eyes, mouths, or
open wounds. Bombardier beetles eject a
noxious spray from their rear end,
filled with irritating chemicals at
nearly boiling temperatures. This is
launched through a buildup of gas like a
natural acid gun and will completely
kill small attacking insects as well as
fend off larger predators. Imagine
trying to spray a bug with raid only for
it to spray you first. Vinegaroones are
arachnids that can also do this except
they spray from their tail the substance
they're named after. Vinegar that's
almost 10 times as strong as the vinegar
used in balsamic salad making it an
irritating and smelly spray to ward off
predators. Because sprayed toxins aren't
transferred through digestion or
contact, it's not called poison. But
because it isn't directly injected, it
isn't called venom either. So, here's
your fun fact of the video. When toxic
substances are projected from a
distance, they're called toxins. Blue
Dragon is a show I watched as a kid that
I feel like no one else remembers but
me. But it's also the name of these
majestic sea slugs. Fitting that their
name matches in animes, seeing as how
they look like Pokémon. I mean, wow. But
don't let these cute looks deceive you.
These guys are very toxinous, though
they actually don't produce any toxins
themselves. Blue dragons feed on
venomous manowar jellyfish and are
immune to the stings of their
nomaticists, instead processing them to
store in their finger-like organels.
Now, they've become able to sting
themselves by releasing these
harpoon-filled cells from their skin.
Horned lizards shoot toxinous blood from
their eyes. And I don't really have much
to say about it. I just had to show you
that that exists. But there are many
other ways to make a spray or slime
dangerous without it being a toxic. The
most famous example raided my garbage
can last week. Skunks have a hole right
above their rectum that produces
something stinkier than any rectum could
be. Their spray has an incredibly
unpleasant odor that's nearly impossible
to get off for days, even with deep
showering, making the investment in
trying to bother them extremely high.
This ability turns them from one of the
cutest animals into an infamous pest
thought of with disgust from humans and
predators alike. Besides spraying, you
often see more viscous substances
secreted as well, like the ink released
by sephopods to escape predators or
inconvenience humans. Velvet worms come
equipped with slime cannons that shoot
out lines of quickly drying adhesives.
This stops their prey from moving so the
worm can approach and consume them
systematically. Similarly, many spiders
use their webs not as passive traps, but
as active tools to ensnare their prey.
Spitting spiders combine venom with
their silk, which they shoot out to
snare and kill their prey from afar.
Bola spiders whip their webs around and
lasso moths from a distance. Ogfaced
spiders create a rectangular net, which
they slam down on their prey. And
triangle weaver spiders wind up their
webs, storing elastic energy, then
releasing to catapult it forward and
snap into prey. Secretions are a rare
yet useful trait to weaponize. And we
see them in a lot of uniquely unpleasant
ways, whether that be toxicity, acidity,
stinkiness, or stickiness. Okay, so
these chemical processes are cool and
all, but sometimes the only weapon you
need is pure blunt force. Whether it be
gorillas slamming their forearms down on
each other or kangaroos throwing drop
kicks with elevated leverage from their
tail or that guy that punched that
kangaroo that time. Sometimes using
whatever limbs we have for movement to
just smash into another animal is a
pretty good way to attack. Flightless
birds like ostriches, casawaries, and
kiwis can dish out some very devastating
kicks. Secretary birds curb stomp cobras
into the ground, grasping their heads
and crushing them to death. Undullets
like horses, giraffes, and deer are also
known to throw up some sweet chin music
through their rear kicks as well.
Heavier animals like hippos, elephant
seals, and large catfish straight up use
their body mass to slam and run over
each other. And birds can use their
wings to smack each other for pretty
minimal damage usually, but it still
works. However, the undisputed king of
striking can again fit in the palm of
your hand. Mantis shrimp have club-like
appendages called smashers, which they
throw forward with the speed of a 22
caliber bullet. These punches can break
apart crab shells, and their fists move
so quickly that water around the punch
starts to boil. I made a couple
wrestling move references earlier, but
obviously in real practice, mixed
martial artists are experts at
weaponizing their bodies. History has
led to so many techniques or styles to
strike as well as grappling techniques
to snap bones, break joints, and put
people to sleep. Anacondas constrict
their prey like a rear naked choke.
Though their thick bodies are obviously
way more optimized at doing this. They
wrap around their prey, squeezing until
there's no blood flow, and they expire
helplessly. Then they go on to swallow
them whole. But if the goal is to be
visceral, limbs can be improved. For no
matter how much martial arts training
you have, a person with a knife will
always be more dangerous. Claws are the
natural knives of the animal kingdom.
Attached to the ends of digits, which
are used to grasp, slash, or crush. Cat
claws are retractable, coming out at
will like hidden blades from Assassin's
Creed. They pounce on their prey,
digging their claws in to hold them
down, then finish them off with powerful
bites to the neck. Some claws are used
less for capture and more for general
tasks like digging holes, grooming, or
climbing. Bears use their massive claws
to strip bark from trees and reveal
tasty insects as well as manipulate
small berries. So, they don't have the
sharpest claws in the shed. Still, a
swipe from them can easily dismember the
largest of animals because bears are
bears. Bird claws are called talons, and
on birds of prey, they're highly
specialized for killing. Harpy eagles
swoop down to crush sloths and monkeys
between their talents, destroying their
bones and killing them instantly. Harpy
eagle claws are as long as bear claws
despite them being so much smaller.
Though as far as birds go, they're
pretty darn huge. But an even bigger
bird is the casawary, which combines
their strong kick with their sharp
talents. They are fast and dangerous,
and many people have been disembowled by
them without even realizing it. I think
this is a good section to mention spurs
as well, which aren't claws, but instead
sharp protrusions of bone. Remember how
I said that wing attacks aren't usually
very damaging? Well, screamers fix that
by having spurs at the tips of their
wings, upgrading them into deadly
swinging hooks. Male platypuses have
spurs by their rear claws, which are
also the source of their potent venom.
This seems to be mainly for male male
competition as their venom glands
enlarge during the mating season only.
While they otherwise produce little to
no venom at all, pinsers are different
from claws. Though they often get called
as such, the more accurate term for a
snipping claw like that of a crab is
achila. Coconut crab keel can crush at
up to 3,000 newtons of force. That's
like a grand piano resting on your hand.
These are used to break open coconuts,
but also on occasion turtle shells as
well as bones. Everything loves breaking
bones. Male fiddler crabs have one
comically large kila and one
regular-sized one. And no, it's not
because they're spending too much time
on only fans. Actually, the opposite.
Their major claws are used to attract
real females by beckoning them over in a
wave. But when another male approaches
the burrow instead, a territorial
dispute goes down where they have an arm
wrestling match and grapple each other
with their major kele until one of them
is flipped over or runs away.
Interestingly, fiddler crabs can be
either left-handed or right-handed. In
most populations, this is split 50/50,
but in some about 90% of them are right
keled, exactly the same as the rate of
right-handedness in humans. The craziest
use of pincers though belongs to the
pistol shrimp which also has one kila
bigger than the other. Except this one
should be spelled k i l a because it is
a literal firearm. They fire with their
arms by snapping their pincers shut so
quickly it creates a cavitation bubble
which bullets forward and collapses
releasing a shock wave that stuns or
kills their prey. This happens in a
fraction of a second, and the force
behind the attack creates a sound louder
than a gunshot and reaches temperatures
close to the surface of the sun, if only
for a brief moment. It should also be
mentioned that the aforementioned mantis
shrimp also strikes so powerfully that
it can create a cavitation bubble and
shock wave, but this isn't the main
point of their attack. Mantis shrimp
also use their raptorial forearms to
grasp and pin down prey. This is another
weapon seen in arthropods like praying
mantids and water bugs. Okay, so
normally this would be the part where I
beg you to subscribe, but today it's
actually going to be the opposite. I
have to thank you for having subscribed.
I grew up watching YouTube. I remember
when they first introduced the 100,000
subscriber play button and thinking what
a dream it would be to get one myself.
Five attempts at a YouTube channel and
over 15 years later, I can finally get
one all because of you guys. So
sincerely, thank you. Your support means
everything. Now, pincers don't only have
to be at the ends of limbs. They're also
commonly found around the mouth in the
form of mandibles. While rhino beetles
have horns, stag beetles have antlers,
which are enlarged mandibles they use to
grapple with each other. They fight to
establish dominance over land with
running sap or rotten fruit because
that's where all the babes are going to
gather, obviously. And then it's king of
the hill. The males grab and try to
throw each other off, aiming to be the
last one standing so that he can guard
the females and the resources. Many
arthropods use mandibles or mandible
equivalents to grasp, crush, or inject
venom. Giant centipedes have modified
two of their front legs into what are
essentially venomous mandibles, but
because they're actually legs, they're
called foripules. Spider mouthpieces are
called keisseray which can come in a
variety of forms and often pack some
venom as well. Alternatively, true bugs
like bed bugs and ambush bugs have
sucking mouthpieces which they use to
pierce and feed on prey or hosts similar
to a mosquito. Assassin bugs sneak up on
their prey and quickly inject their
sucker, letting toxic saliva seep into
them and digest their insides. Some have
been observed carefully tapping spiderw
webs, mimicking the movement of captured
prey, enticing the spider to come over,
only to surprise them by draining their
insides. Another weaponized mouthpiece
are beaks and bills, which come in many
shapes as well. Predatory birds use
their razor sharp beaks along with their
talons in tearing apart flesh, while the
needle-like bills of herand work for
spear fishing by stabbing through their
prey. Here's a great blue heron I saw
the other day. Some are made for
stabbing, some for scooping, and all
sorts of general tasks. But pretty much
every beak can be dangerous when used in
the right way. Alligator snapping
turtles wait in the water, jaws open,
wriggling a fake worm around in its
mouth. When an unsuspecting fish
approaches, they snap their powerful
jaws around them. Their sharp beaks let
them tear through anything and lets them
dig in and hold on so that there is zero
chance of escape. Sephopods also have
beaks lining their mouths, which they
use to break apart prey already caught
in their tentacles. These can break
through crab shells or inject deadly
neurotoxins, depending on the species.
And lastly, swordfish have sharp bills
that they swing around like a blade,
hence the name. This can be used to
slice through multiple prey at once, as
well as seriously injure larger animals.
They've even caused the death of a few
humans and punctured boats in some
cases. Swordfish are one of the fastest
animals in the world with a burst speed
of 97 km an hour or 60 mph, just below
the top speed of a cheetah. It's
possible that their bills help them
reduce drag to reach these speeds,
meaning they aren't only swords to slash
through schools of fish, but to slash
through the water itself. Sometimes,
instead of weaponizing your mouth or
limbs, it's easier to just cover your
entire body. Porcupines are covered in
spiky quills, modified hairs that are
thicker and more rigid, complete with a
needle-like tip. These tips have tiny
backwards facing barbs, making it
extremely painful to try and pull out.
So, predators that have dealt with them
quickly learn that they aren't worth
hunting. A common misconception is that
these quills are shot out, but in
reality, porcupines just back up into
you and leave them in there. Hedgehogs
and akidnas also have spiky quills which
don't detach as easily and so are kind
of just used as a full body armor by
wrapping themselves up into a ball.
Unfortunately, they don't actually drop
rings when you hit them, though. This
isn't dissimilar to puffer fish
inflating themselves to maximize
spikiness or turtles holding up in their
shells, even plants with thorns and
bristles. It's pretty simple. Cover
yourself in something spiky and you'll
be a lot safer from attacks. Tarantulas
aren't just covered in erdicating hairs,
but also actively launch them at their
adversaries. They use their hind legs to
flick these bristle missiles, inflicting
pain, rashes, and allergic reactions.
This attack can even kill small mammals,
and they shoot so much hair it leaves
their abdomen with a bald spot after the
barrage is done. Other animals surround
themselves with spines, like venomous
sea urchants. Lion fish swim around with
their flashy spines flared around them.
This is one of the ocean's most
threatening displays, as these spines
are incredibly toxic, causing most
predators, including sharks, to leave
them alone. Stonefish spines, while less
flashy, are actually much more
dangerous. These are the most venomous
fish in the world, which is odd
considering they don't rely on these
spines too often. They're experts at
camouflage, blending in with the stone
around them to ambush their prey. But
when they get hunted, they're not quick
enough to easily escape. So, their
venomous dorsal spines serve as an
important line of defense. Recently,
some stonefish were found with a
switchblade on their head called a
lacrial saber, which pops out from under
their eyes and locks into place. It also
glows in the dark for some reason. We
don't know why they have this. Stonefish
are already an amalgamation of several
traits, so having a sword on their head
feels a little redundant. Though, the
current thought is that it's used in
tandem with the spines to maximize
defense. This is an example of a natural
weapon that we don't understand the
function of because we've never observed
it being used in the wild. So, just how
many secret weapons do animals have that
we've yet to discover? Oh, by the way,
the stinger or barb of a stingray is
also a spine. Okay, let's move on to
something a little more shocking.
Electric eels are a species of knife
fish, not eels, that can generate a
500vt shock, enough to stun an adult
human and more than enough to stun a
fish for dinner. They produce these
shocks using cells called electroytes,
which comprise into three organs that
make up 80% of the fish's total body
mass. All cells, including our own, send
electrical signals to very small
degrees, and electroytes do this quite a
bit more. Still, it requires stacking
thousands of these cells to get the
shock to be so effective. Some other
fish use electricity as well. There are
the relatives of the electric eel,
including other species of knife fish,
and the electric catfish, which can
produce shocks at up to 350 volts.
Torpedo rays have their electric organs
in their pectoral fins and can produce a
shock up to 220 volts. In ancient
Greece, they were administered as a form
of pain relief, using the shock to numb
the pain of headaches, gout, and
pregnancies, making the electric ray one
of the first narcotics treatments. In
rare cases, light can be used
aggressively as well, not directly as a
weapon, but as a lure in angler fish and
predatory fireflies. Additionally,
cuttlefish have been documented to
change their skin patterns in a rhythmic
way to hypnotize crabs, causing them to
lose all defensive behavior before
crunching down on them with their beaks.
Okay, we've covered some crazy natural
weapons, but what about when animals
expand beyond their own physiology and
use natural tools or the environment
itself as a method of attack? Boxer
crabs carry a venomous sea anemone in
each hand, which they square up and use
as living boxing gloves, complete with a
stinging punch. They're also called pom-
pom crabs because they look like
cheerleaders. This is a unique situation
where an animal picks up another animal
to use as a weapon. They even use the
anemone to pick up small food particles,
so they're kind of like symbiotic hands
as well. If a boxer crab only has one
anemone, it will split it in two,
causing both halves to grow into clones
of each other, ensuring the boxer crab
has a renewable supply of deadly pom
poms. Orcas use the water itself,
speeding themselves through with the
understanding of displacement and
momentum to create a wave above them,
which they slam into unsuspecting prey
above the water. This wave disorients
them and knocks them into the water for
the pod to easily rip apart. Archer fish
can also water bend by pumping water
through their gills to shoot out of
their mouth, sniping prey outside the
water and knocking them in. Ant lions
dig burrows in the sand, using them as
funnels to trap ants. They show a
masterclass in geometric construction,
sloping the walls at the exact angle
that sand is just barely holding on
enough not to slip. Then it buries
itself at the bottom, jaws exposed. And
if they manage to avoid this, the ant
lion will flick sand to avalanche them
down, where they are met with a loving
set of mandibles. As we discussed
before, many animals have lures that
they use to entice prey before pouncing
on them. My favorite, of course, is the
spider-tailed horned viper, which has a
fake spider tail that birds try to eat,
only to quickly be eaten themselves. But
green herand do this without a natural
lure. Instead, they drop insects,
feathers, even bits of bread stolen from
humans to bait fish to the surface, then
spear them for food. There's also that
video of an orca in captivity using one
of its fish to successfully catch a
bird. But, of course, when it comes to
manipulating your environment or
producing your own weapons, humans are
the greatest by far. We started off with
simple spears, clubs, and handaxes.
Then, we threw things like javelins and
slings. Eventually, we melted metal and
made swords and armor and trebuchets and
firearms and fighter jets all the way to
the atomic bomb and more. We have made
weapons of mass destruction and mass
extinction, a power leagues above
anything an organism has ever held
access to. But it took us a long time to
get there. Homo erectus existed for 2
million years before homo sapiens ever
entered onto the scene. And they seem to
have invented the original stone tool
industry. Many animals are seen using
stones for basic tasks like smashing
open nuts and eggs. And some
occasionally use sticks and rocks to
fight. But none of these very
intelligent animals have ever done
something as sophisticated as even the
earliest humans did. Homo erectus took
the time to sharpen their rocks and make
spears which they combined with advanced
strategies and persistence to safely
take down larger animals. This is the
result of evolution as well. Toolm was
so useful for us that we evolved to have
dextrous hands for precise manipulation,
larger brains to create new designs, and
large social groups to pass down
knowledge. These traits developed in our
ancestral environment are the same ones
we've used to make it to the point we're
at today. Our claws are not sharp, our
jaws are pretty weak, and our strength
is often outclassed. We don't seem to
have the natural weapons that would
allow us to face many of the deadly
animals we discuss today. But that's
because our natural weapons are the ones
we made. Another way to look at it is
that we abandoned our natural weapons
because our artificial ones kept things
more flexible. One of the reasons we
think Homo sapiens out competed
Neanderthalss despite them being bigger
and possibly smarter than us is
paradoxically because we were weaker
than them. They used brute force and
simple tools to take down megapana on
the regular. While we were cowards who
couldn't pull that off as frequently and
instead had to think of new ways to
hunt. This led to us throwing spears and
laying traps while the Neanderthalss
continued their high-risk methods of
hunting. Maybe our lack of natural
weapons is the reason we created the
deadliest ones. And whether or not
that's a good thing is yet to be
determined. Okay, thanks for watching.